听译、时间轴：刘巍然（学酥）
接下来 我们将讨论时钟同步
Next, we're going to talk about clock synchronization.
我们已经讲解过 每台计算机都会包含一个石英钟
So, we've established every computer pretty much contains a quartz clock,
计算机没有使用原子钟 因为原子钟过于昂贵也过于庞大
not an atomic clock because atomic clocks are too expensive and too bulky.
我们要做的是 使用没那么精准的石英钟
So, what we need to do is make do with these less accurate quartz clocks,
尝试设计一种机制 让时钟保持相对精准
and we have to somehow try and make the clocks reasonably accurate nevertheless.
石英钟会出现一些漂移
So, these quartz clocks will drift a little bit
因为石英钟的振动频率
because their rate does not match up exactly with
无法完全匹配正确时钟的频率
what the correct clock tick rate should be.
这使得我们要面临时钟偏移问题
And we end up with clock skew.
时钟偏移的意思是 如果我们在同一时刻查看两个不同的时钟
So, clock skew is if we look at two different clocks at the same instant in time,
对比两个时钟的时间戳
and we compare the timestamps from those clocks,
这两个时钟的时间戳会不一样 有一定的时间差
clocks use the difference between those two.
时钟同步想要实现的目标是
And what we want to do with clock synchronization is
让时钟偏移尽可能小
to minimize the skew as much as possible.
我们定义了不同的网络类型
Now, in the types of networks that we have,
在异步网络或部分同步网络中
in asynchronous or partially synchronous networks,
我们无法把时钟偏移量降低到0
it is not possible to reduce the clock skew to 0.
我们能做到的是尽可能降低时钟偏移量
The best we can do is to reduce it as much as we can,
但无论如何降低 时钟总会存在一定程度的偏移量
but there's always going to be a bit of an error tolerance remaining.
实际中一般实现时钟同步的方法是
Now, the way that we typically do clock synchronization in practice is
使用一个叫NTP的协议 即网络时间协议
using a protocol called NTP, the Network Time Protocol.
还有一个叫PTP的协议 但本课程不会介绍PTP协议
There's also another protocol called PTP, but we won't talk about that in this course.
NTP的工作原理是
And the way NTP works is that
假定服务器有一个精准的时钟源
there's a server and we assume the server has some accurate clock source
服务器的时钟源可能是原子钟或者GPS接收器
such as an atomic clock or a GPS receiver.
客户端可以问询服务器 询问服务器的当前时间
And clients can query the server and ask it for the server's current time,
随后 客户端将根据服务端返回的时间调整自己的时间
and then, the client will adjust its own time based on the time that it got from the server.
NTP的应用非常广泛
So, NTP is very widely deployed.
几乎现在使用的所有操作系统都会内置NTP协议
Almost all operating systems that are used nowadays have NTP built in.
例如 macOS中的日期与时间对话框看起来像这样
So, for example, in macOS the settings dialog looks like this.
你可以在这里选择NTP服务器 或者自己输入一个
Here you can choose the NTP server here or type in your own.
我这里将time.euro.apple.com作为我自己的时间服务器
In this case, I've got time.euro.apple.com as my time server.
其他多数操作系统也有一个非常类似的日期与时间对话框
But most other operating systems will have a very similar looking dialog
你也可以调整并选择你想使用的NTP服务器
where also you can adjust and choose your NTP server if you want it.
NTP协议的工作原理是 服务器会分阶层组织
Now, the way that NTP works is that servers are arranged into what are called strata.
阶层0就是一个准确时间源 时间源为原子钟或GPS接收器
So, Stratum 0 is just the accurate time sources, that is, atomic clocks or GPS receivers.
阶层1是一个服务器 此服务器直接与阶层0的时间源相连接
Stratum 1 is a server that is connected directly to a Stratum 0 time source.
阶层2也是一个服务器 此服务器不直接与准确的时间源相连接
Stratum 2 is a server that is not directly connected to an accurate time source,
阶层2的服务器会从阶层1的服务器那里得到时间
but which gets its time from a Stratum 1 server.
阶层3的服务器会从阶层2的服务器那里得到时间 以此类推
And Stratum 3 server gets its clock from a Stratum 2 server, and so on.
协议会使用一系列统计技术和技巧
And so, there are whole bunch of statistical techniques and tricks that are used
尝试提高时间的估计质量
in order to try and improve the quality of our estimates of time.
举例来说 NTP使用的其中一个技巧是
So, one thing that NTP does is, for example,
在条件允许的情况下 问询多个服务器
to query multiple servers if they are available,
因为可能会出现的情况是
because it could be that
其中一个服务器因配置错误等原因出现了故障
one of those servers is misconfigured or it's got a fault or something,
此服务器报告的时间可能会非常不准确
and so, it's reporting a wildly inaccurate time.
因此 如果你问询了三个或五个服务器
And so, if you're querying three servers or five servers,
你可以说其中一个服务器可能出现了异常
then you can to tell if there's one of the servers which is a real outlier.
其他服务器返回的时间都非常接近
and the other servers are all quite close together.
此时 NTP协议就可以排除异常值
In that case, NTP can exclude that outlier,
只保留服务器发来的、看起来更可靠的数据点
and just keep the data points from the servers that seem to be reliable.
另一个使用的技巧是 不止问询一次服务端时间
Another technique that is used is to query a server not just once,
而是在几分钟时间内多次问询服务端时间
but multiple times over the course of several minutes.
我们希望用这种方式
And so, that will then ensure that
消除网络中可能出现的随机网络延迟
at least any random variations in network delay can hopefully get filtered out.
如果网络延时是系统延迟导致的
Now, if there's systematic variations in network delay,
那多次采样结果无法提高准确性
having multiple samples won't help you.
但多次采样结果至少可以帮助我们降低随机误差
But at least multiple samples will reduce the random error.
对于NTP来说 如果你使用的是一个高质量网络连接
And with NTP, if you have a good quality network connection,
那经过同步后 你的时钟与服务器的时钟偏差
it is possible to get your clock synchronized to the server
可以降低到毫秒级
within a couple of milliseconds skew.
如果你使用的是一个低质量网络连接
If you are on a poor-quality network connection,
例如一个繁忙的Wi-Fi连接 或者负载较大的互联网连接
over some kind of busy Wi-Fi, over heavily loaded Internet connection,
则时钟同步的准确性会大大降低
then the accuracy could be much much worse than that.
因此 使用同步时钟假设时要特别小心
So, you always have to be careful when assuming synchronized clocks.
现在 我们来看看
Now, let's have a look at
NTP协议如何估计客户端与服务器的时钟偏移
how NTP estimates the clock skew between the client and the server.
此协议的第一步仍然是向网络中发送一条消息
It works by sending a message over a network, again, as usual.
客户端向服务器发送一条请求消息
So, we have a request message that could send from the client to the server.
当客户端发送的此条消息
And as the client is sending this message,
包含了客户端时钟返回的时间戳
it records the clock according to the client's timestamp,
t_1表示客户端发送此条消息的客户端时间戳
the timestamp t_1, which is the timestamp at which the client sent out this message.
客户端将时间戳t_1拷贝到请求消息中
And it copies that timestamp t_1 into the request message.
NTP服务器收到此消息后
The NTP server, when it receives that message,
也记录下服务器时钟返回的时间戳
it will also record the time according to the server's own clock
t_2表示服务器收到请求时的服务器时间戳
at which it received that message, we'll call that t_2.
现在 服务器需要花费一点时间处理此条消息
Now, the server might take a little bit of time to process the message,
最终 服务器将会回复此条消息
but eventually, the server will reply.
t_3表示服务器发送响应时
And t_3 is the timestamp according to the server’s clock
服务器时钟返回的时间戳
at which the response got sent out.
现在 响应将包含3个时间戳
So now, the response is going to contain all 3 timestamps so far.
t_1只是从请求拷贝到响应中
So, t_1 simply gets copied from the request over to the response.
服务端不对t_1进行任何处理
The server doesn't do anything with t_1.
t_2和t_3来自于服务器的时钟
t_2 and t_3 came from the server’s clock,
分别为服务器收到请求和发送响应的时间戳
as the arrival time and the response time, respectively.
最终 当客户端收到响应时
And finally, when the response is received by the client,
客户端再次记录下收到响应时
the client again records the timestamp according to the client's clock
客户端时钟返回的时间戳
at when that response was received.
我们现在有了4个时间戳
And so, we have now 4 timestamps.
根据这些时间戳
And from those timestamps,
我们尝试计算出两个时钟间的偏移量
we're going to try to work out what the skew is between the two clocks.
首先 我们可以计算出
So, first of all, we can work out
消息在网络中的传输时间
how long that the message is spent traveling through the network.
我们把总网络延迟时间记为δ
And we're going to call that the total network delay δ.
我们首先计算t_4-t_1
And that time has got to be t_4-t_1,
站在客户端的视角看 此时间等于
so, that is the total time that it's spent from the client's point of view
客户端发送请求到收到响应的总时间差
from the time it sent the request to the time it received a response,
再用这个时间差减去服务端的总处理时间
minus the time that the message was spent processing on the server,
也就是减去t_3-t_2 这就是服务端的总处理时间
so, minus t_3-t_2, which is the processing time on the server.
这两个时间差的差值等于
And the remaining time has got to be then the total time
发送的请求和接收的响应在网络中的总时延
that was spent in the network by the response and the request taken together.
现在 我们不知道如何将总时延拆分为发送时延和接收时延
Now, what we don't know is the breakdown of those two,
发送时延为请求在网络中的传输时间
how much time that the request spent in the network,
接收时延为响应在网络中的传输时间
and how much time that the response spent in a network.
你需要两个已完成同步的时钟才能计算出单向网络时延
If you want to work out that one-way network latency, you need synchronized clocks.
但我们这里要完成的工作就是
And the whole point of this exercise here is that
我们没有已完成同步的时钟 我们需要构建同步时钟
we don't have a synchronized clock. We're trying to build a synchronized clock.
因此 我们没办法度量出单向网络时延
So, we don't have a way of measuring that one-way network latency.
我们只能度量出两个网络时延的求和结果
We can only measure the sum of the two network latencies, put together.
但我们可以做一个假设
But what we can do is just make an assumption that
假设两个方向的网络时延是对称相等的
the network latency is symmetric in both directions.
我们假设请求时延等于响应时延
So, we're going to assume that the request latency is the same as the response latency.
如果假设成立 则响应时延等于Δ/2
And if this is true, then the response latency will be Δ/2,
因为响应时延等于总时延的一半
because it's just going to be half of the total delay.
这意味着我们可以估计出
So, this means now we can estimate the timestamp that the server should have
当服务器收到响应时 服务器的时间戳取值
at the moment in time when the response is received by the client.
从客户端的视角看 服务器收到响应的时间戳应为t_4
So, from the client's point of view, it's time t_4.
但我们知道服务器是在t_3发送的响应
But we know that the server sent its response at t_3.
而我们估计出响应的网络传输时延为Δ/2
And we're going to estimate that the response spent Δ/2 traveling through the network.
因此 我们可以估计出
And so, we're going to estimate that at the time
当客户端收到响应时
when the client receives the response,
服务器时钟的时间戳应为t_3+Δ/2
the clock on the server, says t_3+Δ/2, that's our estimate of the server's clock.
估计出服务器的时钟情况后 我们就可以估计出时钟偏移量了
Now that we have an estimate of the server’s clock, we can estimate the clock skew
因为我们可以用估计出的服务器时间戳
because we can just take our estimates of the server’s clock,
减去客户端时间戳t_4
minus t_4, which is the client's clock, and that will give us
这两个时间戳的差值就等于两个时钟的偏移量
the instantaneous difference in time between the two clocks at that moment.
如果将Δ代入到表达式 并对表达式化简
And then, if you substitute in Δ and simplify the expression,
你就得到了这样一个表达式
you get this expression here,
这就是我们得到的时钟偏移量最优估计值
which is our best estimate that we can do of what the clock skew is.
现在 我们估计出了两个时钟的偏移量
Now that we have the skew between the two clocks,
客户端可以修正自己的时钟 从而与服务器的时钟保持同步
the client can correct its own clock and tries to bring it in sync with the server.
此时 客户端的处理方式取决于时钟偏移有多大
And what the client does in that situation now depends on how big the clock skew is.
我们先来看看时钟偏移比较小的情况
So, firstly, let's look at the case where the clock skew is fairly small.
当时钟偏移θ小于125毫秒时
So, let's say θ is less than 125 milliseconds.
客户端的处理方式是
In this case, what the client is going to do is
稍微加快或减慢客户端时钟的频率
to slightly speed up or slow down its clock as necessary,
从而使客户端时钟与服务器时钟保持一致
in order to bring it in line with what the server is.
客户端时钟的频率变化不会超过500ppm
And so, it's going to change its clock rate at most by 500ppm,
即客户端时钟每秒调整量最大不会超过0.5毫秒
so, at most by half a millisecond per second adjustment.
这样一来 我们期望在数分钟后
And so, over the course of a couple of minutes,
客户端时钟与服务器时钟
this means that hopefully the client clock and the server clock
将会逐渐保持同步 收敛到相同的状态
will sort of drift together and converge towards the same state.
在NTP协议中 这一步骤称为倒转时钟
And this is called slewing the clock, that is the term that NTP uses for this.
如果客户端和服务端的时钟偏移量太大了
If the skew is too big between the client and the server,
NTP协议将会步进时钟
then NTP is going to step the clock,
意思是NTP协议将会强制调整时钟
which means it's simply going to forcibly adjust the clock.
这意味着客户端时钟将会突然向前或者向后跳转
So, even if this might mean moving the clock backwards or moving it forward,
客户端时钟将会直接跳转到估计出的服务器时钟状态
but it's just going to jump right to the timestamp estimated from the server clock,
随后 客户端才会再次尝试平滑调整时钟
and from then onwards, it's going to try and do everything smoothly.
这意味着当客户端步进时钟时 时钟会出现不连续的情况
But there is this initial discontinuity of time where the client steps its clock.
最后 NTP还可能出现的一种处理方式是
And finally, it could happen that NTP decides that
客户端和服务端的时钟偏移太大了
the skew between the client and the server is so big
NTP拒绝调整时钟 NTP会说
that NTP refuses to adjust the clock. It just says,
“不 我不会做任何调整”
“No, I'm not going to do anything.”
“我认为一定有什么地方出了大错”
“I'm going to assume that something has gone very wrong.”
“我不知道是客户端的时钟出了大错 还是服务器的时钟出了大错”
“I don't know if the client's clock is very wrong or the server's clock is very wrong.”
“但肯定出现了糟糕的情况 我不会做任何调整”
“But this is just so bad. I'm not going to do anything here.”
“我把问题留给人工操作 让人类自己去解决吧”
“It's going to leave the adjustment for the human operator to solve”.
这也意味着 如果你有一个依赖于时钟同步的软件
So, this means now if you do have software that is relying on clocks being synchronized,
你就必须要特别小心 别让时钟偏移太大
you have to be very careful to actually measure the clock skew between the clocks
确保时钟偏移不要过大
and make sure that it doesn't get too big,
因为NTP客户端可能会处于恐慌状态
because it could happen that an NTP client ends up in this panic state,
拒绝将自己的时钟与服务器时钟同步
and just refuses to sync its clock with the server.
如果NTP客户端认为时钟错的离谱
And so, you've got then an NTP client whose clock is way off.
如果客户端与服务器的时钟偏移超过大约半个小时
It might be half an hour or more wrong compared to the server.
NTP协议就不会纠正客户端时钟了
And NTP is not going to correct it.
因此 如果你有一个依赖于时钟同步的软件
So, you do have to be very careful
你需要特别小心 不能让时钟偏移过大
if you have software that assumes synchronized clocks.
这是调节时钟偏移的一个实例
This is an example of slewing in action.
图中的红线表示两个时钟的偏移量
So, you can see here the red line here is the skew, the offset between the two clocks.
最开始 时钟偏移约为10毫秒
And it starts off at about 10 milliseconds offset
随后 时钟逐渐开始纠偏 最终的时钟偏移量在0毫秒左右摆动
and then the correction gets applied, so that it ends up being round about 0 clock skew.
蓝色线是客户端时钟的节拍率
And the blue line is the tick rate at which the client clock is running.
客户端将自己时钟的节拍率调慢了大约45ppm
And so, the client here has applied slewing up to about minus 45ppm.
这意味着客户端的石英晶体振动频率有一点快
So, that means that the quartz crystal in the client must have been a bit fast.
大约快了45ppm
It was running a bit fast by about 45 ppm.
将石英调慢45ppm后
And by slowing down the quartz by 45 ppm,
NTP客户端将其时钟的节拍率调整到几乎与服务器节拍率相同
now the NTP client has brought the tick rate of the client roughly in line with the server.
现在
So now,
两个时钟的节拍率几乎一致 客户端时钟不再漂移了
both clocks are moving ahead at about the same rate and no longer drifting apart.
调整效果非常好
So, this is very nice.
NTP协议带来的问题是
But the consequence of NTP is that
你在撰写特定代码时要非常小心
you have to be very careful when writing certain pieces of code.
这里给出了一段代码
So, this is a piece of code
大部分软件中都有可能出现类似的这段代码
that is very likely going to occur in all sorts of different software,
这段代码包含了完成某些操作的函数doSomething()
where you have some function that does something, doSomething() here.
你希望度量出这个函数的执行时间
And you want to measure how long that function takes to run.
为了度量出执行时间
And so, in order to measure that time,
你在函数开始执行前先让时钟返回一个时间戳
you simply take a timestamp from the clock before you start the function,
你在函数执行完毕后再让时钟返回一个时间戳
and you take another timestamp after you finish the function,
计算两个时间戳的差值 得到函数的执行时间
and then, you calculate the difference between the two.
这是用Java撰写的一个例子
This is an example here in Java,
但使用其他程序语言也可以撰写出类似的例子
but this could just as well be in any other programming language.
并不只有Java才有这个问题
It's not specific to Java.
这里可能发生的事情是 当你在执行中间的doSomething()函数时
Now, what could happen is that NTP decides to step the clock right
NTP决定步进时钟
while you're in the middle of executing this doSomething() function.
步进时钟意味着
And stepping the clock means that
doSomething()后面的currentTimeMillies()所返回的时间戳
now the timestamp returned by currentTimeMillies() after the doSomething()
可能与前面返回的时间戳有巨大的差距
is going to be somehow wildly different from what it was before.
时钟可能会被回调
So, it could be that the clock was moved backwards,
此时 两个时间戳的差值可能为负
in which case, this difference in timestamps could end up being negative.
如果流逝时间的度量结果是负数
And who knows what your software is going to do
天知道你的软件会出现什么行为
if it measures a negative amount of time elapsed.
软件可能会崩溃 也可能会做出任何有趣的错误行为
Things could crash or things could go badly wrong in all sorts of interesting ways.
两个时间戳的差值也可能会变得大
Also, it could be that this number ends up being far too large
如果NTP在程序中间决定向前步进时钟
because if the NTP client steps the clock forwards,
此时 两个时间戳的差值可能比真正的时间差值大得多
in that case, now it's going to have a much greater timestamp than it ought to be.
差值可能比真正的差值大得多
And so, the difference will be greater than it ought to be.
如果你想度量流逝时间
So, if you want to do this kind of time measurement,
那就不应该使用currentTimeMillis()等依赖时钟的时间度量机制
it is not good to rely on a clock like currentTimeMillis().
你应该使用另一个API
Instead, what you should do is use a different API.
Java提供了另一个函数：System.nanoTime()
So, Java provides this other function here called System.nanoTime().
nanoTime()是针对流逝时间度量任务所设计的函数
And nanoTime() is designed for this kind of thing.
两个函数的表面差异是
So, there's the superficial difference,
currentTimeMillis()使用毫秒 nanoTime()使用纳秒
currentTimeMillis() uses milliseconds, nanoTime() uses nanoseconds.
但这只是两个函数的表面差异
That's just the superficial difference.
真正的差异是 nanoTime()是所谓的单调时钟
The real difference is that nanoTime() is what's called a monotonic clock.
NTP步进时间操作不会影响到单调时钟
And monotonic clock is one in which NTP stepping will not affect it.
也就是说 此类时钟不会突然向前或向后跳转
So, this clock is not going to suddenly jump forwards or backwards.
顾名思义 单调时钟的意思是
As the name says, monotonic clock means that
此时钟会按接近常数的频率向前移动
it moves forward at a more or less constant rate.
时钟倒转仍然会影响到单调时钟 因为时钟倒转会提高时钟的准确性
Slewing will still affect it, because that improves the accuracy of the clock.
但单调时钟不会出现突然跳转 不会出现时钟不连续的情况
But it's not going to suddenly jump with a discontinuity.
使用nanoTime()度量流逝时间
And so, using nanoTime() here to measure the time elapsed
才是正确的方法
is the correct way of doing this.
理解单调时钟和日历时钟的区别是非常重要的
So, this difference between monotonic and time-of-day clocks is very important.
诸如Java的currentTimeMillis()使用的是日历时钟
So, the time-of-day clock is, for example, the Java's currentTimeMillis(),
日历时钟会返回以固定参考点为起始点的流逝时间
which gives you the time elapsed since a fixed reference point.
UNIX时间戳中 固定参考点就是1970年1月1日 即纪元日
In the case of UNIX timestamps, it's this 1st of January 1970, epoch date,
单调时钟会返回任意时刻为起始点的流逝时间
whereas a monotonic clock, the value you get back from it is some arbitrary time
例如 以计算机启动时间为起始点
since, for example, this particular computer booted up.
这意味着此时间戳本身的取值没有任何意义
So, this means that the timestamp by itself doesn't really mean anything.
你不能把这个时间戳通过网络发送给另一台计算机进行比较
You can't send the timestamp over a network to another computer and compare those,
因为两台计算机的启动时间是不同的
because two different computers will have booted up at different times,
不同计算机的单调时钟是不可比较的
and so, their monotonic timestamps are simply not comparable.
但你可以使用单调时钟度量流逝时间
But you can use the monotonic clock for time measurements,
如果你计算单调时钟返回的两个时间戳的差值
because if you calculate the difference between two timestamps from a monotonic clock,
由于在返回的两个时间戳之间
then the time will have moved forward at a near constant rate
单调时钟会按照接近常数的频率向前移动
between those two timestamps,
因此这个差值可以代表流逝时间 是有意义的
and so that's a meaningful measure of time elapsed,
但如果你计算日历时间的差值
whereas if you do that sort of difference with time-of-day clocks,
则NTP时间跳转会影响到此差值
then you are affected by jumping due to NTP.
闰秒也会影响到此差值 我们在前面也讲过这个问题了
You're also affected by leap seconds potentially which we talked about earlier.
因此 使用日历时间戳度量流逝时间可不是个好方法
So, these are very bad for measuring elapsed time.
但另一方面
But on the other hand,
可以在不同的计算机上比较日历时间戳
time-of-day timestamps you can compare across different computers.
我前面提到过TLS证书的例子
If you remember earlier the example I had of the TLS certificate,
TLS证书在特定日期之前是有效的
which was valid until a certain date,
如果我的计算机想检查此证书是否在有效期内
if my computer wants to check whether that certificate is still valid,
我就需要使用准确的当前日期
well, it has to have the accurate current date,
否则 我们就无法对比
otherwise, it's not going to be able to
证书内的时间戳与计算机当前日历的时间戳
compare the timestamp in the certificate with the current timestamp on that computer.
在这种情况下 我们必须使用日历时钟
So, in this case, we do have to use a time-of-day clock,
我们必须跨多台机器同步日历时钟
and we do have to synchronize those clocks across multiple machines,
否则 我们就无法获得准确的日历时间戳了
because otherwise, we won't have accurate timestamps.
正如我前面提到的
So, as I said,
大多数程序语言和操作系统提供了时钟API
many programming languages and operating systems provide APIs for this.
例如 Linux下有一个clock_gettime的系统调用
In Linux, for example, there's the clock_gettime call.
你可以为此调用传入一个参数
And you can pass an argument to it, say, which tells it
告诉此调用你想要实时时钟 也就是日历时钟
whether you want the real-time clock which is the time-of-day clock
还是想要单调时钟
or you want the monotonic clock.
其他语言也会提供类似的API
But in other languages, there will be similar APIs for this.
你需要去查看API的文档
You will have to check the API documentation.
如果你需要度量时间 一定要记住这两个时钟的区别
But it is important to keep in mind this distinction if you do need to measure times.
这两个时钟不光在时间单位上有差异
It's not just about the resolution of the clocks,
单调时钟和非单调时钟本身的差异也非常重要
but the distinction between a monotonic and non-monotonic clock is very important.